[Music]
what's up everyone in today's video
rather than telling you a bunch of
supplements that I've liked I wanted to
show you the thought process I go
through whenever I'm considering
recommending a supplement to my athlete
or myself personally and that's what I
use what I call the supplement decision
tree this is something I develop and it
goes a little something like this
so number one the first thing is we're
going to try to determine whether or not
the supplement is safe now most things
that have gotten through the FDA and
things that are well-known like creatine
caffeine etc are going to be safe when
you consume them at all reasonably right
so anything that's taken that extremely
high dosages beyond recommendations are
gonna be unsafe so that's not really
what I'm talking about here the only
things that are not fall in the safe
category are it's maybe some of the
things bowel hackers are doing or you
know supplements that are you being used
for non and their intended purposes you
can look more into that but then that's
my first line of criteria I'm gonna move
really past this because really if you
take anything at its appropriate dosage
and label recommendations for the
appropriate positions and not mixing
cocktails you're probably going to be
okay here if it fails the safety thing
for the most part the answer is
obviously no you're not gonna take it if
it is safe then I'll move on to the next
criteria all right so let's assume it is
safe and that is work and then this is
where the understanding supplements
becomes very very difficult because
defining whether or not a supplement
quote unquote
works is incredibly difficult now I
could go on for hours and hours here and
probably honestly need to make a fifty
five minute video walking through all
this but I'll give you a little sneak
peek here so a couple things that you
need to do right now so just stop this
video and do what I call a philosophy
check so go ahead and read it on the
screen here and I'll give you a second
right now pause if you have to because
I'm gonna move on I don't know how to
answer this question in fact there is no
answer to this particular question and
this is what I call it a philosophy
check because this is not a decision
about right or wrong this is literally
up to you and your philosophy some
people say in order
me to take a supplement and has to have
have a huge effect
some people say anything more than 1% is
technically in effect why not take it
those people aren't right or wrong
that's just their personal philosophy
and like I said this is a really
intricate conversation we could have but
the end of the day that's your choice
all right so what I want to present to
you is okay know the difference between
data
what's the supplement do what's the
magnitude of effect most likely to
happen in what situations but then
whether or not you determine that as
working boy that's really up to you
right so professional athlete might be
stoked if a supplement gives them 2%
boost your average gym goer is gonna be
pissed thinking they waste their money
because they got slightly 2% better all
right so that's really up to you so
let's move on from work because this is
really what we're talking about right
here's a good example you can see the
cartoon there from hiking artists calm
shout out to them where the hell they
are
but a screwdriver if you try to use it
to hammer in a nail it's a terrible tool
so technically you can say a screwdriver
doesn't work right when in fact every
supplement does something it doesn't may
not work for the purpose you want so you
could be pissed at taking creatine
because it didn't improve your marathon
running distance doesn't mean creatine
doesn't work maybe it doesn't work for
that purpose that analogy can be
extended to basically any supplement say
many of the times I hear people say oh I
took this and it didn't work a lot of
times like well you didn't use a fitted
purpose
that's why or you didn't use it properly
for long enough he took what the wrong
things or the wrong combination so
determining whether or not it works is a
bit more difficult what also makes this
really really complicated is the fact
that you have the concept of the
supplement working so the ingredient but
then you actually have is it is it
active in the particular supplement you
bought and those are two separate levels
that aren't necessarily always the same
one example here I love the quote that
in theory there is no difference between
theory and practice but in practice
there is so for example if you got
stoked about gingko biloba extract and
you can look at the data and determine
whether or not you feel like it works
for inflammation that's actually then
different from buying a gingko biloba
supplement if you don't know if that's
in the supplement you're buying even
though it says I'm gonna label and we
have a huge problem with that especially
with like the herbal supplements so come
back to the work thing that's really
honestly where you need to spend a lot
of your time is determining what works
for you what do you mean by work what's
the situation your context and the
specifics behind whether or not a
supplement quote unquote works for you
that's why I'll never answer that
question on Twitter or Instagram way too
much detail goes into whether it works
alright there's only a few supplements
he'll say yeah basically this works and
I'll leave it at that right but we'll
have to do those in another video maybe
once you've gotten past this whole work
issue you move on in the next step if
not if you determine doesn't work of
course and you obviously know take it if
it does you move on the next step which
I think people skip way too often
and that's lifestyle or food so what I
mean by this is you need to determine if
the problem you're having can be fixed
with whole food first or lifestyle
intervention in my opinion 99% of the
time that's the better step rather than
taking the supplement the easy example
I've given a hundred times on podcasts
and in my book unplugged vitamin D so if
you get a vitamin D level checked and
you are low well one solution would be
to take vitamin D supplements the better
approach though is fix your nutrition or
your lifestyle get out in the Sun more
right that's going to fix the problem
and fix probably many other issues
you're having and it's typically free or
a lot a lot cheaper you also mitigate or
reduce or attenuate or completely
eliminate the problems you have with
supplements like not getting the active
ingredient like being tainted and a
whole other host issues of Co things
being put in the supplement that you
don't necessarily want so the default
should always be can this be fixed
through lifestyle or nutrition if you
feel like you can fix it through
lifestyle nutrition don't take the
supplement if not if you feel like for
example creatine this is not something
you can necessarily fix through exercise
anymore especially if you say you're a
vegan you can't fix it through exercise
and you can't fix it by eating more red
meat which is a primary source of
creatine then you may consider
supplementation but then you have to
determine whether or not it's worth your
money and this is another reason why I
can never answer questions on social
media about is this supplement quote
unquote worth it
because I don't know what you're worth
is an example I'm making what to say
Nathan Tomasello a college wrestler he
has virtually no income it's very very
very low so for him to pay $1,000 a
month for a supplement regimen that gets
him a 3% boost it's not worth it there's
more things we could do for $1,000 I
would improve his performance probably
more than 3% like hire a full-time
physical therapist or massage therapist
whatever
right now another individual Trevor
Bauer professional baseball player
making 15 million a year it's worth it
right and so whether or not a supplement
is worth the money is large part
determined by how much damn money you
have and how bad you want that an
improvement so I can't really ever
answer them so it's another thing you
need to consider is balancing this well
okay it's a 10% improvement probably
over six weeks but it's a hundred bucks
a week for the supplement some people
that's no big deal some people that
money could be better spent higher and
say a full-time nutrition consultant or
a dietician something like that so if
it's not in their formal plan then the
answer is no if it is then the last step
here is actually what I call try and see
so we still really never know any
supplement that's going to work or not
until you try it because we have a lot
of ended enter and intra dividual and
individual differences between people
genetics lifestyles background age etc
so there's no guarantee even with things
that are probably the most well
demonstrated to work caffeine creatine
etc they still don't always work great
and every person so you have to not just
give blank a recommendation but really
implement it and then see if it's
actually working or helping okay outside
of this if you're looking for places to
go to see whether or not
how much does arginine help I want to
know what percent can I expect
improvement in beta alanine you can you
can go for a couple of different places
I recommend examine calm it's it's a
website that is fantastic for providing
you all the peer-reviewed evidence on
any particular supplement basically how
strong the evidence is and at the
magnitude of effect so that's a very
good place I don't have any financial
ties with those guys or anything like
that so that's just a free plug for them
this is good
then one goes to purchasing the
supplement I would look for anything if
you work with an athlete subjected to
water you sought a testing under what's
called informed choice or NSF certified
or anything like that right and you can
see various websites you can give you
can search these websites and find
creatine that is NSF certified or
informed choice for sport or whatever
happened to be so that's it for now I
appreciate it and hope you enjoy
[Music]
you